When it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as what to feed ourselves
and our families,
we should rely not on
anecdotes, but on facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
There is undeniable evidence
that regular physical activity will aid
in the prevention of chronic disease.
But how much
exercise is enough?
Here’s our first story.
Compared
to sedentary individuals,
physically active men
and women may have
an approximately 30 percent
lower risk of premature death.
Even just walking 15 minutes
a day may reduce mortality risk
by 15 percent.
Mortality rates continue
to drop about four percent
for each additional 15 minutes
of moderate exercise a day
like walking, plateauing out
at about 90 minutes a day.
What does that translate to
in terms of time?
The life expectancy for those
walking just 15 minutes a day
would be
about three years longer
compared to those
who don't exercise regularly,
and those meeting
the recommended 30 minutes
a day live
about four years longer.
If you jog a few hours a week
or are in the top five percent
of cardiorespiratory fitness,
you may live five
or six years longer.
Exercising for 20 minutes
may add an hour to your life.
So, for all those who say
they don't have time
to work out,
exercising gives us
like a three-to-one
return on investment.
Give 20 minutes of your life
to get 60 minutes of life.
Beyond that, there's a bit
of diminishing returns,
but exercise an hour a day
and maybe get back more time
than you put in.
The return for vigorous exercise
may be even greater,
as much as seven to one.
An hour of running
could potentially extend
your life seven hours.
Running even 5 to 10 minutes
a day at a jogging pace
(less than six miles
(9.70 km) per hour)
may net the same
longevity benefits
of the 15 minutes
of daily walking.
Similarly, running fifteen
to twenty minutes a day may be
equivalent to walking an hour
a day, and twenty-five minutes
of running can match walking's
maximum mortality benefits
that top off
at around 100 minutes.
The benefits of running,
however, continue to increase
until about 45 minutes a day.
Walking is the most
commonly reported exercise,
and though it is not
as time-effective
as running, it's easier
and safer to start and sustain,
particularly if you,
like much of the population,
are starting out sedentary.
Walking is among the safest
of physical activities,
averaging only about one injury
per thousand hours.
Not using your cell phone
and walking against traffic
when on roads without sidewalks
can reduce pedestrian injuries.
In contrast, nearly 70 percent
of serious runners
become injured over
a year-long period,
suffering most commonly
from knee problems.
There does not appear
to be an increased risk
of knee osteoarthritis, though,
in all but the most elite
long-distance runners who have
about three times higher odds.
Recreational runners
do not appear
to be at higher risk.
The current official
physical activity guidelines
recommend adults get
at least 150 minutes a week
of moderate aerobic exercise,
which comes out to be
a little more
than 20 minutes a day.
That's actually down
from previous recommendations
from the Surgeon General,
the CDC,
and the American College
of Sports Medicine
for at least 30 minutes a day.
This is construed as
a "trade-off between optimizing
health outcomes and minimizing
requirements for individuals."
The exercise authorities
seem to have fallen
into the same trap
as the nutrition authorities,
recommending what they think
may be achievable,
rather than simply informing you
what the science says
and letting you
make up your own mind.
They already emphasize
that any physical activity
is better than none,
so why not stop patronizing
the public and just tell
everyone the truth?
The optimal "dose" of exercise
for maximizing longevity
remains uncertain,
but a pooled analysis
of more than a half million men
and women followed
for an average
of more than a dozen years
found that mortality rates
bottomed out at about 90 minutes
a day of moderate intensity
physical activity
(mostly walking).
Compared
to no regular exercise, though,
exercising
just about 30 minutes a day
gets you about 80 percent
of the way
to that maximum
exercise benefit.
Older adults are also encouraged
to do both muscle strengthening
and flexibility training
at least twice a week,
along with incorporating
balance exercises.
Instead of exercise measured
in minutes,
what about measured in steps?
Nonagenarians—those in their
90s—in the Sardinian blue zone
average about 12,000 steps
a day just living their lives.
Based on a representative sample
of thousands of U.S. adults,
those getting 12,000 steps
a day had a 65 percent
lower risk of dying over
the subsequent decade compared
to those getting only
4,000 steps a day.
Even just getting
8,000 steps a day
appeared to cut the risk
of premature death in half.
A study of more
than 15,000 older U.S. women
found that just 4,400 steps
a day could reduce
mortality rates compared
to 2,700 steps a day,
raising the question:
"Is 4,400 steps per day
the new 10,000 steps per day?"
Where did the 10,000 steps a day
recommendation even come from?
Surprisingly,
it likely originated
as the brand-name
of a Japanese pedometer
sold in 1965 called Manpo-kei
or "10,000 steps meter."
In terms of walking,
the recommendation
for 150 minutes a week
of moderate intensity
aerobic exercise
gets us to approximately
7,000 steps a day.
The maximum longevity dose
of around 90 minutes a day
(technically 22.5 to 40
so-called MET-hours a week)
would give most people a total
of about 13,500 steps per day.
In our next story,
we discover how the evidence
supporting the overall health benefits
of physical activity is overwhelming.
Researchers who accept grants
from the Coca-Cola Company call
physical inactivity "the
greatest public health problem
of the 21st century."
Actually, physical inactivity
ranks down at number 10
for risk factors for death
in the United States
and number 11 for risk factors
for disability.
And globally, in terms of years
of healthy life lost,
inactivity doesn't even break
into the top 20.
As we've learned,
diet is our greatest killer,
followed by smoking.
A media analysis found hundreds
of news articles claiming
that prolonged daily sitting
is as bad or even worse
than smoking.
This is decidedly not the case.
Smoking is expected to cause
a billion deaths this century.
Tobacco is responsible for up
to more than 10 times greater
mortality risk,
comparing the heaviest smokers
versus the heaviest sitters.
What role does physical activity
play in longevity?
In terms of combatting
the hallmarks of aging,
aerobic exercise can induce
autophagy, lower inflammation,
decrease DNA damage,
and facilitate DNA repair.
A meta-analysis of cohort
studies of middle-aged
and older individuals with
follow-ups as long as 20 years
found that exercising adults
were more likely
to age successfully
than sedentary individuals.
Population studies
have found a correlation
between regular aerobic exercise
and decreased risk
of at least 35
different diseases.
But what have interventional
trials proven in terms
of cause-and-effect?
Randomized controlled trials
of older adults
have demonstrated
that physical activity
can improve muscle mass,
strength, balance,
and mobility,
decrease the risk of falls
and potential fractures,
while helping
to minimize bone loss.
Exercise may also
improve cognition, enhance mood,
successfully treat depression
(as well as the prescription of
the antidepressant drug Zoloft),
improve erectile function
in men, and generally improve
quality of life.
The evidence supporting
the overall health benefits
of physical activity
are overwhelming.
Exercise is medicine.
Artery stiffness is recognized
as a barometer of aging,
supporting
the 17th century axiom from
the English Hippocrates that
"man is as old as his arteries."
Normally, large arteries
in the body expand
and recoil with every heartbeat.
(That's the pulse you feel
in your wrist.)
This helps cushion the pressure
waves to prevent damage
to tiny sensitive blood vessels
in organs like your brain
and kidneys.
Thankfully,
not all age-related stiffening
is inevitable.
Endurance training men
and women have artery elasticity
closer to that of younger
sedentary individuals,
a status that can be achieved
after daily brisk walks
or jogging for
just three months.
This may help explain
why those who exercise
appear to live so much longer.
A single exercise session
can improve insulin sensitivity
for up to 17 hours.
Exercise is such powerful
medicine that researchers
at Stanford
and the London School
found that exercise
may work as well as drugs
for patients
with coronary heart disease,
heart failure, and pre-diabetes,
and even better
than some medications
for stroke.
They suggested that
drug companies should perhaps
be required to compare
any new chronic disease drugs
head-to-head against exercise,
as patients deserve
to understand
the relative impact
that physical activity
might have on their condition.
Exercise has been described as
the "only intervention that has
shown a remarkable efficacy
for...increasing mean
and maximum lifespan
in humans."
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
I actually just came out
with another small book:
an easy 100-page read on
Ozempic and other GLP-1 drugs.
Go to NutritionFacts.org
and click on “Books”
to see where you can get an e-book,
audiobook, or paperback of it.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.